A Guide to the Near East Foundation records, Audiovisual Materials, RG 4 FA1307
Rockefeller Archive Center
Near East Foundation records, Audiovisual Materials, RG 4
1954-1971
Rockefeller Archive Center
Near East Foundation
FA1307
42 film reels
- Near East Foundation films, 1; 42 film reels 42 Film Reels, NEF Foundation film collection encompasses approximately 18,000 feet of film on 42 reels. The collection includes 1 negative and 41 prints in 16mm and 35mm formats.
  Conditions Governing Access
  When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  All inquiries to view films require advanced notice of at least 2 business days, and may necessitate notice of up to one week. Individual items, including those that are not available in modern formats, may be restricted from access at the discretion of RAC.
  Arrangement
  Numerical by AV Identification Number
  Scope and Contents
  Amateur films in the Middle East from early to mid 20th century from work done by the Near East Foundation (NEF).
  Sustainable agriculture; Middle East; Iran; Rural development; Amateur films; Documentary films
  - People of Promise: Holy Land, 1958; Silent, Color, 19 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 669 feet, Kodachrome. (Reel AV 958)
    REV. JAMES T. ALBERTSON, PEOPLE OF PROMISE ORG. A home movie of visitors from the NEF Foundation touring the Holy Land admiring the sights of a modern city with art and architechtural history. Film has footage of temples, ancient Egyptian architecture, and street level views of the city. Some rural footage is also present with women and children going about daily activities such as gathering water and cultivating the land with camels. The film ends with examples of popular dance for the locals.
    Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  - People of Promise, Sound, Color, 29 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 1025 feet, Eastman Reversal. (Reel AV 959)
    Amateur film with footage of landscape and points of interest for international visitors including the beach front and interiors of temples. Maps and diagrams help to visualize history. Footage is also captured of locals performing everyday tasks such as adults polishing wood and sewing and children playing with hula hoops.
  - Iran, 1968; Silent, Color, 18 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 658 feet, Kodachrome. (Reel AV 960)
    Amateur film with footage of local farmers working the land. Adults also attend school. Some footage is of ancient artwork including Babalonian artifacts and hieroglyphs. Footage also includes making bread, children playing on swing, and young men honoring the Quran. Nice footage of Mt. Demavand, Persepolis, Tehran, and some young NEF volunteers in the Tehran bazaar.
  - A Helping Hand in the Near East, 1968; Sound, Color, 5 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 177 feet, Eastman Reversal. (Reel AV 961)
    A short film with narration. Footage contains daily life on a farm in the Middle East. A dam and the water one can use help the fields and flowers for gardening.The farmers show off their vegetation. But the locals look forward to new technologies to benefit their agricuture like water pumps.
  - A Helping Hand in the Near East #4, 1968; Silent, Color, 13 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 458 feet, Color Reversal, Awind. (Reel AV 962)
    Film serves as a service announcement for agricutural reform and the bright youngs minds who are using education to help the community. Footage of daily life before change and footage of life after changes with the inclusion of locals drinking clean water.
  - A Helping Hand in the Near East #3, 1968; Sound, Color, 12 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 440 feet, Eastman Reversal, Awind. (Reel AV 963)
    Film serves as a service announcement for agricutural reform and the bright youngs minds who are using education to help the community. Footage of daily life before and after changes with the end result being clean water for the locals. Shows NEF programs: campaign to eradicate Bilharzia in Dezful; the Ahwaz Agricultural College in Khuzistan province.
  - A Helping Hand in the Near East #3, 1957; Silent, Color, 22 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, 818 feet, Eastman Revearsal, Awind. (Reel AV 964)
    Film with narration speaking of a hope for Iran and their 'unproductive earth'. A team of specialists in mechanics, agriculture, sanitation and engineering meet to discuss plans for Iranian villages. The process of sanitation begins by spraying the houses and checking the animals. So that the progress continues men, women, and children are offered education.
  - Near East Adventure #2, 1957; Sound, Color, 22 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 803 feet, Eastman Color. (Reel AV 965)
    Footage consists of farming techniques in Iran. According to narration, the villages have experienced troubles with malaria so steps are taken to protect locals, livestock, and future produce from disease. The film ends with children learning at school.
  - Near East Adventure #4, 1957; Sound, Color, 22 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 815 feet, Eastman Color (Reel AV 966)
    Documentary about NEF's activities in village of Mamazon in Northern Iran, near the Alborz Mountains. Introducing the challenges of traditional agriculture in Iran ("No one on earth works harder than an Iranian farmer"), shows the transformation of the village through a regimen of NEF programs, including a campaign against malaria, the increase in economic productivity through the introduction of tractors, wells, and pumps for drinking water. Social changes include the first local elections, with footage of the voting process and the use of cutout shapes as ballots b/c of the villagers' illiteracy. Also shows efforts to eradicate this illiteracy through programs for women & the elderly.
  - Near East Adventure #4, 1957; Sound, Color, 24 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 864 feet. (Reel AV 967)
    Same footage as AV 965 & AV 966.
  - Syria, 1958; Silent, Color, 5 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, printm, 176 feet, Kodachrome. (Reel AV 968)
    Footage inside and outside of the city. Inside the city, the architecture and artifacts are a quiet reminder of the past while bustling street scenes are a reminder of the modernization in place. Mountains are visable in the distance.
  - Middle East Religious Sites, 1958; Silent, Color, 8 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 305 feet, Kodachrome. (Reel AV 969)
    Visitors sightsee by visiting temples and lakes while also stopping to take a group photo. Different modes of transportation are observed.
  - Arab Village- The Story of Merj, 1956; Sound, Color, 8 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 340 feet, Eastman Color, Awind. (Reel AV 970)
    Footage of current agricultural technologies and tasks such as water collecting and tending the livestock. Men can be seen having discussions at a meeting while women and children visit the doctor. Same as AV 998.
  - Lebanon, 1959; Silent, Color, 9 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 214 feet, Kodachrome. (Reel AV 971)
    A more industrial look at the Middle east. This amatuer film captures industrial sites -buildings with pipes and valves- for daily opporation. Views of a ship at sea from the shore. Children are also seen at school.
  - Athens - Iran #3, 1969; Silent, Color, 12 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 428 feet, Eastman Reversal. (Reel AV 972)
    Mostly still life footage of natural landscapes and vegetation. There is also footage of city buildings in contrast to domed roof huts. In this film, children make numurous appearances acknowledging the camera. By Rev. James T. Albertson of Central Methodist Church and an NEF board member.
  - Jordan, 1964; Silent, Color, 16 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 564 feet, Kodachrome. (Reel AV 973)
    This film contains aerial shots of both city and countryside from a distance. During visits to historical/religious sites, some visitors meet a religious elder, examine tapestry designs, view ancient scrolls, and visit what appears to be tombs. Some recreational activity such as floating on the beach and swimming take place. A J.T. Albertson Film
  - The Bible Lands, 1961; Sound, Color, 26 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 946 feet, Eastman Reversal. (Reel AV 974)
    Tourists visit Israel and partake in activities such as water sports, entertainment, and sightseeing. The city has a market with goods to admire including art, tapestries, metal works, and sculpting. Camels rides offers transportation to the Egyptian pyramids. Produced by Pan American Airlines.
  - The Dyke, Sound, Black & white, 22 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 803 feet, Ferrania stock. (Reel AV 975)
    This short film captures the hardships and victories met by a village when the building of a dam is underway. From flooding to rocky soil, the whole village works together so that they can celebrate the future of a plentiful harvest.
  - Korea - The Enlightened Village, Sound, Black & White.; 16mm, Acetate, print, Gevaert Stock. (Reel AV 976)
  - Candle in the Dark, 1970; Silent, Color.; 16mm, Acetate, print, Kodachrome. (Reel AV 979)
  - Boys Haven and Amman Boys Club, 1970; Silent, Black & white, 8 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 271 feet, Awind. (Reel AV 981)
    Majority of footage is a montage of still photography. Footage shows the bunkhouse and classroom of the Boys Haven. Boys learn trades like sewing and wood work while enjoying games such as Dominoes and Chess.
  - Morocco, 1954; Silent, Color, 24 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 854 feet, Kodachrome. (Reel AV 983)
    Footage of cityscape and the markets and wares one can find on the streets. Crafts include plates and dishes, wood carving, musicians with dancers, exterior decorations, and animal performers. An appearance of the peace sign from a man waving to the camera. Rural footage is included such as a man made river, mountains, and farmland.
  - Tour of the Holy Land, 1960; Silent, Color.; 16mm, Acetate, print, Kodachrome. (Reel AV 987)
    Amateur film capturing city monuments such as the colliseum, ancient gardens, and temples with statuary.
  - The Middle East, 16mm, Acetate, Negative. (Reel AV 988)
  - Gaza and the Refugees, 1959; Silent, Color, 12 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 432 feet, Awind. (Reel AV 989)
    A film with footage of Gaza locals watching military personal demonstrate techniques used in combat. The women also show flag motions they sign with. Children receive food and eat outside after locals obtain bleached flour.
  - NEF Reel 1, Sound, Black & white, 10 minutes.; 35mm, Acetate, print, 351 feet, Agfa stock. (Reel AV 990)
    NARRATED IN PERSIAN WITH PERSIAN TITLES; series of short films documenting what appears to be the immediate aftermath of the 1978 earthquake in Tabas.Reel One: Images of the devastation and of bodies being pulled from rubble.
  - NEF Reel 2, Sound, Black & white, 7 minutes.; 35mm, Acetate, print, 257 feet, Agfa stock. (Reel AV 991)
    series of short films documenting what appears to be the immediate aftermath of the 1978 earthquake in Tabas. Reel Two: Scenes of death, grief and mourning.
  - NEF Reel 3, Sound, Black & white, 6 minutes.; 35mm, Acetate, print, 202 feet, Agfa Stock. (Reel AV 992)
    Series of short films documenting what appears to be the immediate aftermath of the 1978 earthquake in Tabas. Reel Three: A visit by government officials, maybe including Prime Minister Amir Abbas Hoveyda.
  - NEF Reel 4, Sound, Black & white, 10 minutes.; 35mm, Acetate, print, 344 feet, Agfa stock. (Reel AV 993)
    series of short films documenting what appears to be the immediate aftermath of the 1978 earthquake in Tabas. Reel Four: The Shah and Queen Farah arrive to survey the destruction and to visit survivors.
  - NEF Reel 5, Sound, Black & white, 8 minutes.; 35mm, Acetate, print, 288 feet, Agfa Stock. (Reel AV 994)
    series of short films documenting what appears to be the immediate aftermath of the 1978 earthquake in Tabas. Reel Five: The Royal visit continued; footage of the relief effort and of ordinary Iranians donating money and goods.
  - Here They Are in Their True Colors, 1955; Silent, Tinting/Toning.; 16mm, Acetate, print, Kodacolor. (Reel AV 995)
  - W2C, 1953; Sound, Black & white, 1 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 42 feet. (Reel AV 996)
    Footage from a conference showcasing the table for "The American Friends of the Middle East"
  - Athens - Iran, 1968; Silent, Color, 10 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 369 feet, Kodachrome. (Reel AV 997)
    Footage of ancient architecture in Athens including the Acropolis and ampitheaters. Some trades are demonstrated such as iron refurbishing, manikin making, and broom making. Children wave to camer then show some athletic activities.
  - The Story of Merj, 1951-1971; Sound, Black & white, 14 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 509 feet. (Reel AV 998)
    Footage of current agricultural technologies and tasks such as water collecting and tending the livestock. Men can be seen having discussions at a meeting while women and children visit the doctor. Same as AV 998. Same as AV 970.
  - Israel, 1958; Silent, Color, 10 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 352 feet, Kodachrome. (Reel AV 999)
    Amateur film of the city and the surrounding rural areas. A look at the life of a local village.
  - Egypt 1959, 1964; Silent, Color, 19 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 675 feet, Kodachrome. (Reel AV 1000)
    Footage of sights one can see in Egypt. Architectural buildings such as temples are admired. Sailboats can be seen on the river. Even some views of the streets are present.
  - Holy Land - Jerusalem - Emmans, 1958; Silent, Color, 5 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 186 feet, Kodachrome, Awind. (Reel AV 1001)
    Footage of city. Some rocky hills on the outskirts are explored and and a stone table is a point of interest.
  - Athens, 1968; Silent, Color, 7 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 237 feet, Kodachrome, Awind. (Reel AV 1002)
    Film sppears to be a video following patients in a Grecian hospital/ clinic. A nurse and some patients are introduced. A handicapped man demonstrates how to exercise and a boy is taought how to lace a boot. School children demostrate exercise regimen. Same as 1003
  - Athens #2, 1969; Silent, Color, 10 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 369 feet, Kodachrome, Awind. (Reel AV 1003)
    Film sppears to be a video following patients in a Grecian hospital/ clinic. A nurse and some patients are introduced. A handicapped man demonstrates how to exercise and a boy is taought how to lace a boot. School children demostrate exercise regimen. Same as 1002
  - Athens - City, Acropolis, etc., 1969; Silent, Color, 11 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 382 feet, Kodachrome, Awind. (Reel AV 1004)
    Footage of ancient architecture in Athens including the Acropolis and ampitheaters. Some natural sites are visited such as some rocky hills and floral gardens.
  - Tour the Holy Land, 1961; Silent, Color, 31 minutes.; 16mm, Acetate, print, 1142 feet, Eastman Color. (Reel AV 1673)
    A Summary of the trip taken to the Middle East. Footage incorporates tourist attractions such as the Egyptian Pyramids and religious sites while also including rural landscapes and the locals who inhabit the area. Lastly, visitors also enjoyed the nearby sea/river.
  - #1 - #5, 1956; Silent, Black & White/ Color.; 16mm, Acetate, print, Kodachrome. (Reel AV 1742)
- Near East Foundation audio, 2
  - Sadik Al-Assad, Nuhad J. Daghir -I / Nuhad J. Daghir -2, Rajah Tannous (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6896)
  - Dr. Winnie Huoho - 2, Blind woman, anatomy class, Wayne Jones (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6897)
  - Untitled (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6898)
  - HAMLIN HOSPITAL: Linda Londers (tours), children's song - Nasla Vuch / Dr. Charles K. Nucho -I (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6899)
  - Abdul Latif El-Zerin - 2, Nasri S. Kawar - I / Paris Andreou XI, Abdul Latif El-Zein - I (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6900)
  - Untitled (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6901)